Finding Aid for the Yvar Mikhashoff Collection of Annotated Scores, 1828-1993
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Yvar Mikhashoff Collection of Annotated Scores, 1828-1993
Mus. Arc. 1.7
Mikhashoff, Yvar, 1941-1993
57 boxes (1353 folders)
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
The collection contains approximately 1300 scores, half of which bear markings entered by Mikhashoff or his colleagues in preparation for performance. The collection includes manuscripts and print publications, both originals and reproductions.
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
Materials can be examined by qualified researchers in the Music Library during hours of operation during which Music Librarians are present. In order to insure access, researchers are advised to contact the Music Library in advance of visits.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the estate of Yvar Mikhashoff, 1993. Additions in 2016 from Amy Williams.
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Biographical Note
Yvar-Emilian Mikhashoff was born Ronald MacKay in Troy near Albany, New York in 1941. He began piano studies with Betty Weir and Stanley Hummel in Albany. At the Eastman School of Music in 1959, he first took a major in composition and cello, then changed to piano studies with Armand Basile. In the 1961 academic year, he studied piano at the Juilliard School in New York City. He also had a career as a ballroom dancer from 1962-1965.
In 1964 Mikhashoff entered the University of Houston for studies in piano with Albert Hirsh. He earned a B.M. in 1967 and continued with graduate study in composition with Elmer Schoettle and obtained his M.M. in 1968. It was during this period that MacKay adopted his grandfather's name, Mikhashoff.
Receiving a Fulbright scholarship in 1968, he studied the music of the French Impressionists with Nadia Boulanger. After his return to the United States, Mikhashoff entered the University of Texas at Austin as a doctoral candidate in composition and studied with Hunter Johnson, Kent Kennan, Janet McGaughey and Karl Korte. He earned a Doctor of Musical Arts degree with a major in composition and a minor in literature in August 1973 and founded the Cambiata Soloists ensemble. In the fall of 1973 Mikhashoff was appointed Assistant Professor in the Music Department at the State University of New York at Buffalo. Based in Buffalo until his death in 1993, Mikhashoff had an international performing career which led him to promote new music and American music around the world.
Mikhashoff had a genius for programming, a talent he utilized extensively while organizing many festivals and broadcasts of new music throughout the world, including his work at the Almedia Festival in London and the Holland Festival. Mikhashoff co-founded the North American New Music Festival in 1983 with Jan Williams and remained a co-director until his death. He commissioned works from such notable composers as John Cage, Lukas Foss, Otto Luening, Poul Ruders, James Sellars, Christian Wolff, and many others. One of his most notable commissioning projects occurred in 1982 when he commissioned or solicited new tangos for solo piano from an international array of more than 80 composers. Mikhashoff also edited publications of music, including works by Henry Cowell, Lejaren Hiller, Conlon Nancarrow, and Virgil Thomson. He recorded on the New Albion, Mode, RCA Victor, CRI, and Spectrum record labels. Yvar Mikhashoff's support of contemporary music continues today through the Yvar Mikhashoff Trust for New Music which was created by his estate to support composers and performers of new music.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains approximately 1200 scores, chiefly for solo piano but also including other vocal and instrumental combinations. More than half the collection consists of photocopied scores, and there are more than 550 manuscripts and holographs (original and photocopy).
The collection was initially processed and described by Matthew Sheehy in 1997. The current description is expanded both in terms of the level of detail provided, the range of dates represented in the collection (thus the disparity between the earliest date (1762) now stated in the collection versus the date of 1828 in the title of the collection), and also by the inclusion of additional works identified after the initial inventory was prepared. Also, some works in the series of unmarked scores are individually noted as having markings due to later examination. The major portion of the additions consists of works that Mikhashoff grouped together. They reflect some of his research interests and themes associated with concert programs he presented. These groupings include folders of material related to composers, including Lukas Foss's Solo for piano, composed for Mikhashoff, Charles Ives's Second piano sonata (Concord sonata), Sylvano Bussotti's Racine, pianobar pour Phèdre, a collection of works by Percy Grainger, and Virgil Thomson's series of musical portraits. Thematic programs include the concerts titled The Golden Clavier, Hollywood elegies, Miss Jane's parlor, Opera matinee, and From Vienna to New York. There are also groupings for the works Mikhashoff collected for his Melodeclamation concerts and for the Buffalo Piano Collection that he compiled.
The range of repertoire, chiefly from the 19th and 20th centuries, is impressively broad. While Mikhashoff was best known for his performances of contemporary music, his research uncovered many works of the piano repertoire from many lesser-known composers, some of whom are now forgotten or rarely performed. The list of composers included in the collection is indicative of Mikhashoff's involvement in contemporary music in America and internationally.
More than half of the scores contain annotations made by Mikhashoff in preparation for performance. The markings represent Mikhashoff's entire career: from markings on piano exercises such as Czerny's School of velocity, marked for Mikhashoff's piano lessons at age fourteen in 1955, through works composed for him during his last year of life. Many scores bear only incidental markings but there are also scores that are extensively marked. Mikhashoff sometimes re-notated works or passages from works, usually to make them more legible. Mikhashoff's versions of Foss's Solo for piano and Virgil Thomson's Nineteen portraits for piano were used for the published versions of those works.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into seven series:
I. Annotated scores
II. Unmarked scores
III. Oversized
IV. Additional annotated scores
V. Additional unmarked scores
VI. Composer groupings
VII. Program and thematic groupings
VIII. Additional annotated scores received 2016
IX. Additional unmarked scores received 2016
Container List
- Annotated scores 1762-1993, I.; Folder 001-Folder 607
  Chiefly arranged in alphabetical order by composer surname and then alphabetically by title.
  - Adams, John, 1947- Grand pianola music, undated, 1 score (32 pages); Reproduction of manuscript piano 2 part only G. S. Schirmer Instrumentation: For double woodwind, double brass with one tuba, 3 percussionists, 3 wordless female singers, and 2 pianos "Perf. Nov. 27, 1987, Huddersfield, Adams, conductor". Second piano part contains performance markings. Contains markings for performance. Signed by Mikhashoff. (Box 01, Folder 0001)
  - Albeniz, Isaac, 1860-1909 Iberia: volume 1, 1962, 1 score (35 pages); Print Kalmus Instrumentation: For solo piano Contains very small number of performance markings. (Box 01, Folder 0002)
    Evocation -- El puerto -- Fete-dieu a Seville
  - Albeniz, Isaac, 1860-1909 Iberia: volume III, undated, 1 score (46 pages); Print Kalmus Instrumentation: For solo piano Performance markings on EL elbaicin only (Box 01, Folder 0003)
    EL elbaicin -- El polo -- Lavapies
  - Lyon, James, 1735-1794 Urania. Selections, 1762, 7 scores; Photocopy Instrumentation: For 2-4 voices, arranged for strings Markings for instrumentation only. From collection compiled by Mikhashoff titled Americana: Psalm tunes. (Box 01, Folder 0004)
    Includes 8th, 23rd, 95th, 136th, two celebrated verses by Sernhold and Hopkins, 150th and 104th psalms
  - Antheil, George, 1900-1959 Sonata no. 2 for violin, piano, and drums, undated, 1 score (18 pages); Manuscript Instrumentation: For violin, piano, and drums Contains some piano fingerings, violin bowings, corrections to accidentals, and other incidental changes. (Box 01, Folder 0005)
  - Apostel, Hans Erich, 1901-1972 Kubiniana: zehn Klavierstücke, 1947, 1 score (16 pages); Print (photocopy) Universal Edition Instrumentation: For solo piano Contains piano fingerings. (Box 01, Folder 0006)
  - Argento, Dominick From the diary of Virginia Woolf, 1975, 1 score (42 pages); Print Boosey & Hawkes Instrumentation: For medium voice and piano Contains some performance markings and notes about the use of the 12-tone row in the piece. Signed by Mikhashoff. Additional name: Woolf, Virginia, 1882-1941 (Box 01, Folder 0007)
  - Arne, Thomas Augustine, 1710-1778 Soldier tired of war's alarms arranged for flute and voice, undated, 2 scores (4 pages each) and 1 part (2 pages); Manuscript (photocopy) Instrumentation: For flute, voice, and violoncello Contains some performance markings. From Arne's Artaxerxes. (Box 01, Folder 0008)
  - Arne, Thomas Augustine, 1710-1778 Soldier tired of war's alarm, undated, 1 score (3 pages); Manuscript Instrumentation: Piano reduction Includes changes to the score. From Arne's Artaxerxes; transcribed down a whole step, in Mikhashoff's hand. (Box 01, Folder 0009)
  - Auric, Georges, 1899-1983 Alphabet, 1924, 1 score (10 pages); Print (photocopy) M. Eschig Instrumentation: Originally for voice and piano Marked with instrumentation for arrangement for piccolo, oboe, bassoon, violin, viola, and violoncello (Box 01, Folder 0010)
    Album -- Bateau -- Domino -- Filet à papillons --Mallarmé -- Hirondelle -- Escarpin
  - Babbitt, Milton, 1916-2011 Tableaux: for piano, 1978, 1 score (30 pages); Manuscript (Ozalid copy) C. F. Peters Instrumentation: For solo piano All dynamics on first page highlighted with colors. (Box 01, Folder 0011)
  - Bach, Johann Sebastian, 1685-1750 Concerto [in] A minor for four cembali and string orchestra [BWV 1065], 1931, 1 score (58 pages); Print Eulenburg Instrumentation: For four pianos and string orchestra Only markings consist of score system divisions and one tempo marking. Miniature score. Transcribed from the Concerto for 4 violins and string orchestra in B minor by Antonio Vivaldi. Signed by Joseph Wincenc. Additional name: Vivaldi, Antonio, 1678-1741 (Box 01, Folder 0012)
  - Bach, Johann Sebastian, 1685-1750 Six English suites, 1945, 1 score (86 pages); Print Kalmus Instrumentation: For solo keyboard Suites 2 and 3 marked for performance. Missing title page and final page of music. (Box 01, Folder 0013)
  - Bach, Wilhelm Friedemann, 1710-1784 Sonata pour 2 clavecins (F. 10), 1910, 1 score (20 pages); Print Durand Instrumentation: For two keyboards Contains keyboard fingerings. Brittle. (Box 01, Folder 0014)
    2 printed scores, for two performers.
  - Baker, Larry, 1948- Double, 1977, 1 score (8 pages); Manuscript (Ozalid copy) Instrumentation: For solo piano Marked with some changes and additions to interpretative markings. "Ed. By Y. Mikhashoff Aug. 1978"--Caption. (Box 01, Folder 0015)
  - Baker, Larry, 1948- Homage to D, 1976, 1 score (7 pages); Manuscript (Ozalid copy) Instrumentation: For solo piano Marked with a few metric counters. (Box 01, Folder 0016)
  - Barber, Samuel, 1910-1981 Anthony and Cleopatra. Libretto, 1966, 21 pages; Print G. Schirmer Instrumentation: Libretto Some text bracketed. Signed by Mikhashoff. Additional name: Zeffirelli, Franco (Box 01, Folder 0017)
  - Barber, Samuel, 1910-1981 Sonata op. 6: for violoncello and piano, 1936, 1 score (27 pages); Print G. Schirmer Instrumentation: For violoncello and piano Prepared for performance with some markings and photocopied pages added to facilitate page turns. Signed by Mikhashoff. (Box 01, Folder 0018)
  - Barber, Samuel, 1910-1981 Toccata festiva, op. 36, 1961, 1 score (39 pages); Print G. Schirmer Instrumentation: Originally for organ and orchestra; score for organ and piano Contains performance markings. (Box 01, Folder 0019)
  - Barry, Gerald, 1952- Au Milieu, 1993, 1 score (17 pages); Print (photocopy) Oxford University Press Instrumentation: For solo piano Photocopy of "1st proof" with marked corrections. (Box 01, Folder 0020)
  - Barry, Gerald, 1952- Sur les pointes, 1981, 1 score (18 pages); Manuscript (photocopy) Instrumentation: For solo piano Systems crossed out on pages 16-18. (Box 01, Folder 0021)
  - Bartók, Béla, 1881-1945 Improvisations on Hungarian peasant songs: opus 20, 1939, 1 score (16 pages); Print Boosey & Hawkes Instrumentation: For solo piano Extensively marked for performance, including addition of texts of the Hungarian folksongs. Signed "Ronald MacKay" (Box 01, Folder 0022)
  - Bartók, Béla, 1881-1945 Mikrokosmos: volume IV-VI, 1967, 3 scores; Print Boosey & Hawkes Instrumentation: For solo piano Contains few markings for performance and a few pieces are marked with instrumentations for arrangements. (Box 01, Folder 0023)
  - Bartók, Béla, 1881-1945 Rumanian folk dances, 1945, 1 score (9 pages); Print Boosey & Hawkes Instrumentation: For solo piano Contains performance markings. (Box 01, Folder 0024)
  - Bartók, Béla, 1881-1945 Seven pieces from Mikrokosmos: for two pianos, four hands, 1947, 1 score (34 pages); Print Boosey & Hawkes Instrumentation: For two pianos, four hands Contains some performance markings, including fingerings and durations. Signed by Mikhashoff. (Box 01, Folder 0025)
  - Bartók, Béla, 1881-1945 Studies: opus 18, 1948, 1 score (20 pages); Print Boosey & Hawkes Instrumentation: For solo piano Contains very few performance markings. (Box 02, Folder 0026)
  - Bartók, Béla, 1881-1945 Suite: opus 14, 1939, 1 score (19 pages); Print Boosey & Hawkes Instrumentation: For solo piano Contains some performance markings. (Box 02, Folder 0027)
  - Beeson, Jack, 1921-2010 Fifth piano sonata, 1973, 1 score (11 pages); Print T. Presser Instrumentation: For solo piano Contains a few performance markings. "Facsimile edition of the manuscript of the editor, John Kirkpatrick. Program for Mikhashoff May 4, 1980 performance attached inside front cover. (Box 02, Folder 0028)
  - Beethoven, Ludwig van, 1770-1827 32 sonatas for the piano: volume 1 (no. 1-17), 1935, 1 score (411 pages); Print Simon and Schuster Instrumentation: For solo piano Contains relatively few performance markings on a few works. Edited by Artur Schnabel (1882-1951). (Box 02, Folder 0029)
  - Beethoven, Ludwig van, 1770-1827 Fourth concerto, op. 58, 1929, 1 score (76 pages); Print G. Schirmer Instrumentation: Originally for piano and orchestra; score for two piano reduction Contains performance markings. Orchestral accompaniment arranged for piano by Franz Kullak. (Box 02, Folder 0030)
  - Beethoven, Ludwig van, 1770-1827 Sonatas for piano: volume 1 (no. 1 to 15), 1952, 1 score (248 pages); Print Kalmus Instrumentation: For solo piano Contains some performance markings. Signed "Ronald MacKay". (Box 02, Folder 0031)
  - Beethoven, Ludwig van, 1770-1827 Sonatas for the piano: in three books: book I (sonatas 1-11), 1923, 1 score (214 pages); Print Schirmer Instrumentation: For solo piano Some fingerings on first sonata only. (Box 02, Folder 0032)
  - Bennett, Mark, composer Drunken boat, 1988, 1 score (31 pages); Manuscript (photocopy) Instrumentation: For tape, piano, and narrator Contains some performance markings and corrections. "For Paul Schmidt and Yvar Mikhashoff". Text by Arthur Rimbaud, translated by Paul Schmidt. Additional name: Rimbaud, Arthur, 1854-1891 (Box 02, Folder 0033)
  - Bennett, Mark, composer War songs, 1990, 1 score (30 pages); Manuscript (Computer notation print) Instrumentation: For speaker, violin, oboe, clarinet (B-flat), cello, and piano Contains performance markings. Text by Paul Schmidt, film by Lawrence Brose. Additional name: Schmidt, Paul, 1934- (Box 02, Folder 0034)
  - Berberian, Cathy Morsicat(h)y, 1971, 1 score (12 pages); Print Universal Edition Instrumentation: For solo piano Contains manuscript of realization by Mikhashoff. Signed by Mikhashoff. Realization "Transmitted by telephone from Milano to Breukeleu at 4:30 p.m. March 4, 1981". (Box 02, Folder 0035)
  - Berezowsky, Nicolai, 1900-1953 Slow waltzes for Babar, 1953, 1 score (3 pages); Print (photocopy) C. Fischer Instrumentation: For solo piano Contains some performance instructions. Selections from Babar the elephant, a children's opera. (Box 02, Folder 0036)
  - Berg, Gunnar, 1909-1989 Gaffky's assortiment 2, 1971, 1 score (10 pages); Print Samfundet til udgivelse as Dansk Musik Instrumentation: For solo piano Contains a small number of performance markings. (Box 02, Folder 0037)
  - Berio, Luciano, 1925-2003 O King, 1970, 8 leaves; Print (photocopy) Universal Edition Instrumentation: For mezzo soprano, flute, clarinet, piano, violin, and violoncello Some parts contain minimal performance markings. Four parts for flute, clarinet, violin, and violoncello created by cutting from full score and taping to cardboard sheets. (Box 02, Folder 0038)
  - Berners, Gerald Hugh Tyrwhitt-Wilson, Baron, 1883-1950 Trois petites marches funebres, 1920, 1 score (10 pages); Print (photocopy) J. & W. Chester Instrumentation: For solo piano Duration of second movement marked. (Box 03, Folder 0039)
  - Bernstein, Leonard, 1918-1990 Age of anxiety: Symphony no. 2 for piano and orchestra, 1966, 1 score (94 pages); Print Amberson Instrumentation: Two piano score Contains performance markings. (Box 03, Folder 0040)
  - Bernstein, Leonard, 1918-1990 Age of anxiety: Symphony no. 2 for piano and orchestra. The masque, 1966, 1 score (pages 72-93 on 11 leaves); Print (photocopy) Schirmer Instrumentation: For piano and orchestra Percussion parts identified. (Box 03, Folder 0041)
  - Biscardi, Chester Piano concerto: for piano and orchestra, 1985, 1 score (25 pages); Print Instrumentation: Piano part only Contains extensive performance markings. Signed by Mikhashoff. (Box 03, Folder 0042)
  - Blake, Eubie, 1887-1983 Melodie: Capricious Harlem, 1936, 1 score (6 pages); Print (photocopy) Instrumentation: For solo piano Markings include some measure numbers, changes to pitches, and signs for instrumentation. (Box 03, Folder 0043)
  - Bowles, Paul, 1910-1999 [Little suite], 1939, 2 scores (17, 21 pages); Manuscript (photocopy) Instrumentation: Instrumental parts for two pianos Parts marked Minnie and Mickey. Mickey part contains some performance markings. Incidental music to a Mickey Mouse cartoon. Original held in the Bowles collection at the Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center at the University of Texas at Austin. (Box 03, Folder 0044)
  - Bowles, Paul, 1910-1999 Milk train doesn't stop here anymore, undated, 1 score (22 pages) and 4 parts; Manuscript (photocopy) Instrumentation: For instrumental ensemble: celeste, percussion, English horn/oboe, guitar/mandolin, and harp Score and parts marked for performance. Incidental music to the play by Tennessee Williams. There are 3 copies of the score and 2 sets of the parts. Accompanied by text of the play marked with cues. Original held in the Bowles collection at the Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center at the University of Texas at Austin. Additional name: Williams, Tennessee, 1911-1983 (Box 03, Folder 0045)
  - Bowles, Paul, 1910-1999 Summer and smoke, undated, 1 score (47 leaves); Manuscript (photocopy) Instrumentation: For instrumental ensemble Score marked for performance. Accompanied by notes about changes. Incidental music to the play by Tennessee Williams. Original held in the Bowles collection at the Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center at the University of Texas at Austin. Additional name: Williams, Tennessee, 1911-1983 (Box 03, Folder 0046)
  - Brahms, Johannes, 1833-1897 Horn trio, op. 40, undated, 2 scores (39 pages each); Print C. F. Peters Instrumentation: For piano, violin, and horn Both scores marked for performance. Signed by Mikhashoff. (Box 03, Folder 0047)
  - Brahms, Johannes, 1833-1897 Liebeslieder Walzer op. 52, 1961, 1 score (49 pages); Print Lawson-Gould Instrumentation: For 4-part chorus with piano 4-hands accompaniment Contains small number of performance markings. Edited by Robert Shaw. (Box 03, Folder 0048)
  - Brant, Henry, 1913-2008 Hand organ music, 1933, 1 score (9 pages); Holograph (photocopy) Instrumentation: For two pianos Contains small number of performance markings. (Box 03, Folder 0049)
  - Brant, Henry, 1913-2008 Inside track, 1982, 1 piano part (33 pages); Manuscript (Ozalid copy) Instrumentation: Concerto for solo piano and three separated instrumental groups and projected images Marked for performance. Piano part only. (Box 03, Folder 0050)
  - Brant, Henry, 1913-2008 Spatial concerto: Questions from Genesis, 1976, 1 piano part (38 pages); Manuscript (photocopy) Instrumentation: For solo piano with orchestra divided into widely separated groups, and ensemble of women's voices (8 Sopranos, 8 Altos) The part is marked "Inside Track, for piano and small orchestra" before first system of music but the score does not match the piano part for that work. No other markings. Score compiled from individual systems for piano from the score. (Box 03, Folder 0051)
  - Bright, Colin Night, 1976, 1 score (12 pages); Holograph (Ozalid copy) Instrumentation: For piano, bass, and vocal sounds Contains a few annotations to the written performance instructions. (Box 03, Folder 0052)
  - Britten, Benjamin, 1913-1976 Death in Venice [selections], 1975, 28 photocopied leaves from vocal score; Print (photocopy) Faber Instrumentation: Piano vocal score for opera Three divisions marked: Scene on the beach no. 1, no. 2, and no. 3. Rationale for page groupings not immediately evident. Libretto by Myfanwy Piper, based on the short story by Thomas Mann. (Box 03, Folder 0053)
  - Britten, Benjamin, 1913-1976 Serenade: for tenor solo, horn and strings, [op. 31, vocal score], 1944, 1 score (44 pages) and 1 part; Print Boosey & Hawkes Instrumentation: for tenor solo, horn and strings; accompaniment arranged for piano Contains some performance markings. (Box 03, Folder 0054)
  - Brouwer, Leo, 1939- Regin mas transparente: for flute and piano, 1984, 1 score (15 pages) and 1 part (7 pages); Print Editions Musicales Transatlantiques Instrumentation: For flute and piano Contains only a few markings. (Box 03, Folder 0055)
  - Brown, Earle, 1926-2002 Folio [and] 4 systems, 1961, 2 folders; Print (Reproduction of holograph) Associated Music Instrumentation: For various unspecified instrumental ensembles Copy marked Extra contains performance markings. Unmarked copy includes a transparency with a treble/bass clef system to overlay the diagrammatic notation of December 1952. Copy marked Extra also includes a marked photocopy of the prefatory note and two manuscript pages of music realizations of December 1952. Both scores are complete but some pages in each are photocopies rather than original pages. (Box 03, Folder 0056)
  - Brown, R. D., composer 3 chapters for piano, 1973, 1 score (12 pages); Holograph (photocopy) Instrumentation: For solo piano Only a small number of markings. (Box 04, Folder 0057)
  - Busoni, Ferruccio, 1866-1924 Klavierübung. Selections, 1922-1925, 1 score (3 pages); Print (photocopy) Breitkopf und Hartel Instrumentation: For solo piano One dynamic marking. Selections taped together into new sequence; taken from different books and editions. (Box 04, Folder 0058)